One of the quotes that came out of
Anthropic was MCP is like the USB-C for
AI.
>> I love the analogy. If anybody has a
USB-C, it can be used for a variety of
different devices, and the same is true
for MCP. As soon as an MCP server is
implemented for a particular data set,
API, or service, that same MCP server
can be used in any client, whether it be
ChatGPT or Anthropic or an AI agent that
is created in a kind of bespoke manner
to do a variety of different tasks.
>> So, as a plug-in person, when I saw MCP
announced, this was very clear to me
that this was the plug-in system for all
AI software. And if we can accept the
fact that all software is going to
become AI software, then this MCP is the
kind of plug-in system that matters.
>> How far are we from people being able to
truly trust MCP servers? And what, in
your experience, is that level of trust
in the industry?
>> really trust any just off-the-shelf MCP
server because
>> Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So, whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast is for you.
A really quick ask, 90% of people who
are listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So, if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. All
right, back to the episode.
>> Hello and welcome to another episode of
the AI Native Dev. We've got a fun
discussion here today talking about all
things MCP. We're going to go into the
depths of what MCP is, the various
architectural pieces of MCP, talk a
little bit about something called MCP
Run, which is a super interesting tool
that allows you to use other people's
MCP servers. It's a hosted environment
that allows you to also to run tasks
against various MCP services. We'll take
a a bit of a deep dive into that. We'll
also talk a little bit about what's new
in the in the world of Anthropic with
the new MCP registry and talk about what
MCP looks like for the future as well
for for developers and industry. And
joining me on this journey is Steve
Manuel and Steve is the founder and CEO
of Dilipso. Steve, welcome. How are you?
>> Very well. Thanks for having me Simon.
>> Oh, absolute pleasure. And where abouts
you calling from today, Steve?
>> I'm in the San Francisco Bay Area.
>> Oh, nice. The heart of AI in the US,
right?
>> Exactly. We're all locked in here.
>> Yeah, and so let me guess you go to a
you go to a an AI meetup every what?
About three times an evening? Is that is
that about right?
>> Exactly, yeah.
>> Awesome. So Steve, tell us a little bit
about yourself, a little bit about your
journey with with through MCP actually
as well cuz obviously it's not it's not
MCP's not been out for a huge amount of
time but there's been so much
innovation. I'd love to hear a little
bit about kind of like you know how you
how you started with MCP and how you you
know built things like MCP run and
things like that going forward.
>> Sure. Totally. So yeah,
I
I kind of got started on the MCP journey
by accident largely.
The company Dilipso
since its inception has been working on
computer isolation technology through
WebAssembly for the purpose of plugin
systems. Largely for making apps
extensible beyond their original design
and functionality.
Enabling an end user to kind of
customize the application experience by
actually injecting new code into that
application
through the security of model security
model of the
WebAssembly runtimes and code execution
environments. This actually is kind of a
practical safe way to extend
third-party software. And so as a plugin
person when I saw MCP announced now in
November of 2024 like 10 years ago it
feels like
this was very clear to me that this was
the plug-in system for all AI software
and if we could accept the fact that all
software is going to become AI software
then this MCP is the kind of plug-in
system that matters. So we we very
quickly were early to adopt MCP and
implement the protocol on top of our
isolation wasm stack
and that since has you know become
a whole whole kind of interesting
dynamic for the company and has
presented new opportunities for us to
firstly bring our extensibility
technology into a new space but also
just explore how else we can bring
useful features and functionality into
applications through the virtue of MCP
as kind of the connector layer between
systems and
AI large language models.
>> Very interesting. One of the one of the
I probably overused quotes that came out
of Anthropic was how MCP is like the
USBC for AI and that makes a ton of
sense but one of the things that makes
USBC super interesting and valuable is
the fact that it uses the same the same
API I guess
and and that API obviously connects
everywhere. People know how to use it.
What is it that MCP solves that existing
API patterns don't?
>> I love the analogy
and I think it makes you know perfect
sense to explain it this way because if
you think about USBC as more of a
connection port as like a you know a way
to interconnect different things
be it a phone or a computer or a camera
the cable that connects those two
devices
is standardized and so if anybody has a
USBC
just laying around, it can be used for
a variety of different devices. And the
same is true for MCP. As soon as an MCP
server is implemented for a particular
data set, API, or service,
that same MCP server can be used in any
endpoint, any client, whether it be
ChatGPT or Anthropic or an AI agent
that is is, you know, created, you know,
in a kind of bespoke manner
to do a variety of different tasks. It
really is this kind of now like write
once, run anywhere
eventuality. And I'm mentioning this I
think particularly because you're
wearing this Java shirt.
And allows, you know, any system to
communicate with another over this
standard.
The problem really that at its core that
I think pushed the Anthropic team to
firstly, you know, devise the standard
and then open source it and release it.
You know, and I'm I'm sure many of the
people on the core team will be angry
that I
specifically narrow the problem down to
tools.
But function calling, tool calling, tool
use in agents and models is not a new
capability. However,
every single model and library and
framework had a different way of
describing how tools should be used, how
the parameters are provided, how the
values are returned, and a different
format for kind of laying out what that
tool looked like. So, what is the
signature of the name? Is it a JSON
file? Is it described through, you know,
just free-form text? And
it meant that everybody had to basically
rewrite their tools or at least the tool
interface between different
models or agent frameworks. And it just
was very cumbersome to do that. I think
Anthropic, you know, rightly was uh
you know, realized that they could do
something here to improve that and make
it easier for people to share and reuse
these implementations The across a
variety of different
tools and services.
>> And it's funny cuz when they released
that yeah, like you said, a couple of
decades ago in November of 2024,
um
it was it was almost quite a
quiet launch. It was like there was
nothing huge made out of it. But I think
we looked at it and we you see the raw
potential that this could potentially
you know, that this could have on on
LLMs and and how how powerful how this
empowers them really
to to to to kind of like make those
decisions. And exactly like you say,
it's that in that standardized way that
really unlocks it across models. I guess
you mentioned a few terms there. Let's
let's let's kind of go in and demystify
a few of those terms. So, there's
obviously the protocol. Let's talk a
little bit about the protocol as well.
You've got the protocol that kind of
like works between
client and server and then you have
obviously the MCP client, the MCP
server. Talk us through the the
architectural pieces here of of where
things sit, what we develop, why we
would use one over the other.
>> Sure. So,
firstly, the protocol is kind of split
in two
segments like like many protocols are,
especially the client-server variety,
just like HTTP.
MCP is broken into a a server
and a client. And a server is basically
the way you communicate with some
upstream data source or service. You
know, how do I get access to do the
action or to read the email or to
call some system that provides some
additional context to a model. And the
client is kind of this interceptor
between the server and the model
that is actually communicating over the
protocol to get that data or call that
tool or manage some resource.
And the client is
right next to the
uh, model. Um,
usually they're they're contained inside
what the spec defines as a host. And
um, so that could be chat GPT or cloud
desktop or it could be an AI agent um,
that's running that has access to tools.
An MCP client is the side of the
implementation that knows how to
discover and connect to an MCP server
and then also to call the various um,
spec functionalities like listing tools
or calling tools or finding resources.
>> That that that's all I could see there.
>> General high-level overview.
>> Yeah, yeah, absolutely. So So when we
think about the the, you know, the
clients obviously we, you know, we
install these clients onto our onto
cloud desktop or onto cloud code or or
however we whatever we want to we were
wherever we want to use, you know, MCP
servers.
Um, the servers though,
one of the one of the big challenges is
really identifying which servers we want
to use, that discoverability of servers.
Um, and of course this is kind of like
where a ton of all these registries and
things like that sit. Um, want to you
give us an intro into into uh, mcp.run.
It's super cool how I guess
um,
you know, there's this a number of
registries out there that kind of like,
you know, perform these collations of of
servers that you can use.
The mcp.run, which we'll talk about in a
in a little sec, goes that step further
and allows you to actually, you know,
perform activities or tasks on top of
these servers that exist. But but talk
us a little bit through, you know, what
a registry is, how we use a registry and
and a little bit about mcp.run.
>> Sure.
So first um, everybody should be aware
that Anthropic as well as the community
group that works on the protocol um,
have established an official registry,
which is really exciting,
uh, that supports um, kind of a
the collection and discovery of MCP
servers implemented across the
ecosystem. And the goal, and I don't I
don't want to speak for for them uh, but
I'm just going to regurgitate a little
bit of what, you know, is is already
published is to provide a
kind of universal and discoverable layer
of infrastructure that provides, you
know, pointers and, you know, listings
of MCP servers that are hosted even on
other registries or out on GitHub or
anywhere else. Um and the the goal is to
serve the community to also be able to
build sub-registries on top of this
registry. So, perhaps, you know, there
is a vertical focused registry that's
adjusted for marketing tools or just for
developer tools or just for, you know,
financial services. The goal is to be
able to support, you know, more focused
sub-registries that can all pull from
this this registry. So, just a shout out
to the teams
um largely from Block, um Pulse MCP, and
Throped and more um who've been putting
in the hours uh to to get this this up
stood up. Um
It it's a really neat uh implementation
uh and it's all open source. Um so, go
check that out. Yeah, yeah, discovery is
challenging. I think when when MCP was
first announced, there was this sprawl
of, you know, software engineers who,
you know,
were basically like hooking up kind of
CLI apps, you know, local executables uh
into these chat applications and um your
best bet was to kind of just like look
through GitHub to try to find, you know,
someone's NPM library that presented as
an MCP server. Um and you know, it was
it was smart to kind of figure we need
some place to make it easy to find
high-quality MCP servers, but also to
secure uh the ecosystem through
identity. Make sure that whoever's
publishing MCP servers can prove uh that
they're publishing something um that
they own that that is, you know,
trustable. Uh there's still a lot of
work to do on kind of the trust and
quality management perspective, but um
at least it's a step in the right
direction to have, you know, a large
global um
you know, universal registry to to
manage MCP servers. Um, before Entropic,
um, and the organizing group around the
spec did the work to create an official
registry, um, many other companies or
organizations or teams worked on
registries, uh, so that we could fill
the gap until there was something
official.
And, um, so ourselves,
um, and many other companies, uh, have
put some work in to hosting registries.
Um,
ours is a little bit different in that,
uh, mcp.run,
um, hosts user code, uh, that that is
implemented implements MCP servers from
WebAssembly modules. And, um,
this allows us to execute their code in,
you know, a very
isolated environment, um,
and and brings a level of security that
just kind of can't be matched with other
technology for the same efficiency and
cost and performance trade-offs. So,
instead of running Docker images or, uh,
you know, a whole virtual machine, um,
we can just run a little function inside
of WebAssembly module, uh, that
implements the tool calls.
Um, not a super critical detail, um,
but the the goal has always been to kind
of provide the most secure, uh,
environment for,
you know, third-party code to execute on
our platform. Um,
but we're also seeing largely that many
MCP servers are moving to their own
remote hosts. So, PayPal, GitHub, um,
many other companies are realizing we
should just publish an endpoint like we
do in HTTP API, uh, that allows a more
kind of agent-oriented,
uh, client to access and use our
service. So, we're we're excited by, I
think, this move to official MCP servers
hosted by their first-party provider
kind of being the,
uh eventuality.
>> It's It's It's really interesting, isn't
it, when you see and, you know, just
then when you kind of when you kind of
talk through that, my me and my uh
background as Sneak, I kind of I kind of
shudder every time I hear certain things
like, you know, with my background in
the open source, third-party libraries
with certain vulnerabilities and and
malicious libraries and things like
that, the potential for something quite
damaging is is is you know, pretty
pretty pretty damaging. It's pretty big.
>> Yeah.
>> But um it's it's all about how do we
actually how do we actually put the um
put the precautions in place so that we
we limit the the potential blast radius.
What you're talking about here where
it's like it's more containerized, it's
running in isolation, those kind of
things really really really really good.
The idea of and I've used MCP servers
before, I've looked at other people's,
you know, GitHub repos and I'm like, "Oh
gosh, now I've got to do a full code
review of this cuz I want to I want to
understand, you know, is this is this
actually legit or is this, you know,
looking a bit dodgy?" Um the idea of,
you know, third parties running MCP
servers kind of like scares me a bit,
but then, you know, when you know it's a
validated MCP server from a trusted
source, okay, then it's just, you know,
it's a potentially just another service
that they're offering on the on the
interwebs. How far are we from people
being able to truly trust
uh you know, what they see from MCP
servers? And and what in your experience
is that level of trust in the industry?
So, you know, are you seeing this pick
up from startups, from from mid-size
companies, from enterprises that are
that are actually, you know, fully using
MCP servers in production today?
>> Yeah, definitely. I mean, it was
surprising when MCP was first announced
that there was, you know, a relative
lull around the excitement and interest.
Um
and I think that
initially, it was kind of too oriented
for developers. And developers quickly
saw that there was potential here, there
was something exciting here. And, you
know, we saw this explosive growth then
in kind of the earlier half of 2025.
Now, we're seeing that um
the technology and the protocol have
been implemented enough in a variety of
different clients uh
that they're
visible to a non-technical audience. And
so, what we see um is absolutely at
every level of, you know, company size,
from startup all the way up to very
large, you know,
even even regulated industry like banks
and financial services uh are starting
to realize that if they're going to give
their employees access to AI for
productivity, the the logical next step
is to also have that AI be connected to
some of their internal workplace
applications and services. So, um we see
people connecting this into Salesforce
or HubSpot or CRMs to do prospecting and
lead enhancement and and and um
content generation like, you know,
writing emails for you, responding to
emails, customer service is big. You
know, there's a company called Intercom
who has a an agent named Finn.
And Finn implemented MCP so that
customer service teams can attach
services um and tools to Finn, and Finn
can do more, you know, proactive data
lookups or actions against, you know,
the customer support queries it's it's
handling.
Um
So, I think like it's it's definitely
escaped the kind of developer chambers
and is now in um the the real world. Uh
and to go back to your question on
trust, like this poses a huge problem um
because you can't really trust
any just off-the-shelf MCP server you
find. And this is coming from somebody
who runs an MCP service, who I would of
course love everybody to trust us, but
it's just you can't trust anything um
because you don't know what exactly is
happening behind the scenes. What's What
actually happens when you call that tool
um
with whatever data the model has decided
to extract from your prompt and send off
to that MCP server.
So there there is a substantial
challenge so to
you know, figure out with regard to
trust. But I think that the first step
is actually just using the MCP servers
that are from the providers themselves.
Just like you would trust any normal uh
HTTP API that you interface with to you
know, a service like Spotify or PayPal
or Google.
Um
they should and hopefully will at some
point provide a you know, first-party
MCP server
because that that that does alleviate
some of the you know, trust concerns.
>> Yeah, absolutely. I think it I think
it's when there isn't a a provider's own
MCP server that it starts, you know,
bringing questions up. I mean, I know,
you know, we had a that's a a good
session with
with someone off air actually where they
were talking about how they can how
they've almost like built up their own
their own almost like, you know,
assistant where it consumes all of their
calendar information, all of their email
information, all of their notion and
linear data and they have they have
stacks of information that that can kind
of
you know, give the LLM information about
who they are, what they're what what
they like doing, what what what are the
what are the things that they that they
care about in their career that they
want to absolutely nail. And then it
uses these MCPs to pull all that data.
And of course, there are so many there
are so few MCP servers that are from the
originating company that you know, the
actual provider company, you're you're
relying on these third-party
open-source tools to handle your most
sensitive data. And it can cause huge
product productivity gains if if you get
this right, but you are you are opening
yourself up a little bit. I think
there's I'd love to talk about the
difference between almost managed versus
self-hosted
MCP servers here. If I'm if I'm
self-hosting myself, I'm running this
maybe even locally, for example, the
risk is much much lower, but I have to
trust the the the MCP server is is, you
know, doing the right things with the
data I'm passing it and and and handling
that correctly. Um but managed servers,
managed MCP servers, there's there's
there's, you know, a bunch of other, uh,
you know, valid things that that that
will offer us as well that our laptops
and and local machines
just can't do at scale. Talk us through
what that, you know, when a developer
thinks, "Okay, should I go to that
remote or should I host this locally or
do it on my machine and STD
you know,
STDIO kind of,
um,
spin off of an MCP server?" What is What
is the right choice when?
>> I'm more and more convinced that
standard IO MCP servers are never the
right choice. Well, unless you're
writing it yourself, the risk is
substantial and the risks are now, um,
at the level of your machine with the
same privileges that you as the user of
your machine have.
And so if if if that MCP server is just
running on your laptop, it has the
ability to read your environment
variables, it has the ability to call
the network in any fashion it likes
using any protocol and any tools it
likes.
It has the ability to read and write to
your file system and this is like kind
of the, you know, red alert, highest
severity problem, uh, that a user of an
MCP server will face. So, the movement
of these MCP servers up to managed
endpoints remotely or in the cloud, um,
removes a whole layer of security risk
that is down at the endpoint down at the
client computer, the user's machine.
However, there are definitely times
where you kind of need to have a
standard IO MCP server if you're largely
working with developer tools and then
you need to call a CLI that's on your
machine or if your code project is only
local to your machine and an MCP server
is operating on diagnostics from your
IDE or something like that. You can't
get that up in the cloud unless you're
using some, you know, kind of managed
cloud code generating platform. I think
you guys probably know a couple good
ones there. So, I I I think largely, you
know, the remote MCP servers are the
more secure ones, um,
but you also need to trust that the
endpoint is authentic and you need to be
able to connect to it and authenticate
to it.
Um,
so I don't think there's a a, you know,
hard and fast rule as to like which is
the better,
you know, transport to use for an MCP
server, whether be standard IO or
remote. I think it's very situationally
relevant to say, "Okay, well, what what
kind of data am I using? Where does the
data live? What is the authentication,
you know, what is the security risk?"
And, you know,
the reason all these transports exist is
because they have, you know, their own
time and place to use them.
Um, but I think we're moving away from a
local standard IO based MCP server that
executes on the user's machine, um,
just because there there's there are
more implementations of MCP servers
remotely, um,
and I think those are far easier to
trust. Um, now,
running an MCP server remotely
in your own infrastructure versus
just connecting to a remote URL that is
provided over the internet, uh, are also
two different things. You can implement
an MCP server that wraps an API because
the API provider themselves don't
provide an MCP server and absolutely run
that yourself, um, host it in your own
network, and connect to it through, um,
you know, your
infrastructure.
Um,
we we see many many companies deciding
to move in that direction just for the
control and the transparency over what
tools are, you know, being connected to
by MCP clients that their teams are
using.
Um, and to plug a product, we do
actually have kind of a self-hosted MCP
platform, um,
that provides this level of
transparency, auditability, security, go
to Turbo MCP.
Um, and this was largely a learning, um,
from providing mcp.run. Um, large
organizations and folks who are more
concerned about security aren't going to
trust a public proxy to take this MCP
traffic from an MCP client and
transmit, you know, whatever sensitive
information from a database or a SaaS
product through a public proxy up to its
upstream service.
Um, and so, in order to kind of satisfy
that need of controlling that proxy and
owning that traffic, um, you know, we
did build a self-hosted version of
mcp.run, but it's a little more kind of
a larger, kind of more security-oriented
enterprise customer. For individuals,
you know, using public proxies is still
fine. Um, but you're but you're
definitely taking on a little bit of
risk just to trust that entity that
you're not going to
send off my Notion page data or my
calendar data up to some, you know,
advertising service or, um, if you get
hacked, then, well, you have all my auth
tokens and all of the, you know, plain
text data that was extracted from,
you know, my email, uh, that's maybe
sitting inside your database somewhere.
>> Mhm. So, mcp.run is fully managed then
by yourselves and and and Turbo MCP is
is self-hosted that I can just come
along and stand up an instance in my
organization and and then start running
straight away against that.
>> Correct.
>> There are two types of things that you
can host on there. One is MCP servers,
the other is uh, servlets. And I kind of
like when I saw that I thought, "Wow, I
I haven't heard or read the word servlet
in many, many years." And I thought,
"Wow, have we come that far that
actually we can we can we can override
the term servlet and there's not there's
not enough contention still on our I I
shed a tear for for that moment. Um but
tell us what what's the difference in a
servlet and a full MCP server?
>> Yeah, a servlet has literally nothing to
do with the spec or MCP at all. It's a
term that we chose very, very early on
and
if we could rewind the clock, maybe we
wouldn't have used this term. But it's
it's just too perfect of a term to not
have used. In the Java world, a servlet
is basically an implementation of a
subset of HTTP so that you can reprogram
a HTTP server
that runs in Java with what they call
the servlet that allows you to basically
intercept an HTTP request, run some
code, and then return an HTTP response
back up to the host application. And
what an MCP.run servlet is is a subset
of MCP that allows you to just handle
intercept a tool call
and implement the tool call and respond
with a tool call uh result. And so it
allowed us to basically simplify the
implementation of MCP so that a
developer only had to worry about
implementing the tool call functions
that they wanted to support as opposed
to standing up an entire MCP server in
which you need to pick a transport, you
need to figure out authentication
scheme, you need to figure out um many,
many things that are just like not the
core business of
implementing a tool. So yeah, a servlet
is kind of our our our toy term for the
simplification of MCP on MCP.run and the
ability to kind of like
go serverless, do no infrastructure,
just ship a little function that
implements the tool just like a Java
servlet allowed you just to ship a
little bit of code inside the, you know,
wrapper of a HTTP service.
>> Love it. Love it. And And what are
You're not going to release applets as
well, are you?
>> No, we're going to save the world all
that trouble.
>> Yeah, it's a Talking of security
problems.
Um No, that makes sense. That makes
sense. And And so, from as a developer,
um if I wanted to build on top of
mcp.run or rather,
um if I if I wanted to to to to submit,
I guess, and deploy a tool on mcp.run,
um what is the What What is my
development life cycle here look like in
terms of how I do that?
>> So, yeah, mcp.run is actually powered by
another
uh service that our company builds
called XTP,
uh which is largely a plugin system as a
service. So, if you wanted to add a
plugin system to your application, XTP
makes it very easy to integrate other
third-party code that's from your
customers or users and execute that code
inside of your application.
And
um mcp.run, you know, builds on top of
this, you know, code execution uh
technology. And so, you are basically as
a as a developer who wants to publish to
mcp.run are interfacing with kind of the
service behind the scenes, XTP. And so,
there's some tool reuse. You download a
CLI, and this CLI allows you to
bootstrap into a MCP servlet project.
So, you can pick a language you want to
implement it in, whether that be
JavaScript, Zig, Rust, Go, Python, C#,
C++, and we drop you into kind of a
boilerplate project. And that project
basically has two functions. One
function to be implemented is the tool
call handler, and the other is the
description of the tools. And as the
developer, you fill in the
implementations. Here's a tool called,
you know, get email, and it actually
then it goes and connects to the Gmail
API or whatever, and does a search based
on input parameters that you defined in
the description, and then returns back a
tool call result. The goal is, you know,
we drop everybody in these kind of very
well-typed boilerplate functions,
um so that you have, you know, rich
types that help auto complete and, you
know, make the developer experience
rather nice.
Um
There is a caveat here that all of these
implementations compile to WebAssembly
modules, and so there there are
limitations that come inherently with
that, uh but they limitations are
purposeful so that you don't run into
these kinds of security problems that
any other form of implementing an MCP
server would have, in the sense that if
I'm running an untrusted MCP server,
and I authenticate to my Gmail through
it, that MCP server has my token, my
access credential to that upstream
service,
but it also has the ability to send my
data to some other server, because once
the data enters the MCP server, it's
somebody else's code working inside of
that, and they could choose to just
write your email list to disk, or they
could send it off to some third-party
server, and you wouldn't know the
better. So, one of the features of
WebAssembly and our particular
implementation is that we require, when
an MCP server is registered by the
developer who wants to publish it, that
they include a allow list of domains
that that that the code will potentially
reach out to, allow list a set of
environment variables that uh that code
will need at runtime, and allow list,
you know, if they need file system,
which paths that or directories ahead of
time that that code wants access to to
be approved. And then when the user of
that MCP server installs it on mcp.run,
they allow that those domains,
environment variables,
and file paths are are made available to
the code. So, you're very aware as the
end user that this Gmail MCP servlet is
actually only ever talking to
api.google.com,
never to any nefarious third-party
server that the developer may have
access to or is leaking information to.
So, you're sure that your data is
staying where you expect it to stay, uh
which is
at least a helpful starting point to
reduce some of the the risk here.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Absolutely. And I
think it follows a lot of the best
practices there. Very similar to kind of
like apps on a marketplace, what they
have access to, those types of things.
Absolutely. And And we've talked a lot
about the security, I guess, of how uh
I, as a consumer of an MCP service, want
to make sure that that MCP server is is
um you know, legitimate, doing the right
things, those types of things. If we
consider now, okay, that's a that's an
absolutely legitimate uh MCP server
that's running somewhere,
um somewhere hosted, and how do I make
sure uh that the security of now the
person who's actually going to be using
that is actually authorized uh to to be
able to access the data they say they
can. What What are the um
How do we What's the security model
behind that handling of authorization,
authentication, those types of things?
>> Yeah, absolutely. This was um
This was kind of one of the larger
problems the protocol faced in the
earliest days just because there really
was no
standard or recommendation on how to do
this. So, everybody was kind of
implementing, you know, hacks in many
ways to get authorization uh or to get
kind of authentication data into this um
into the transport in order to send a
token or a key or whatever off to the a
service.
Um now, uh the protocol has adopted um
OAuth
2 a particular subset of OAuth uh called
dynamic client registration
so that you can integrate your MCP
server um against, you know, otherwise
already standardized implementations of
auth flows. Uh and this makes it much
easier for a user of the MCP server to
effectively like delegate access to an
AI agent or application
to use their
upstream service like Slack or
Salesforce or whatever um through
a very simple like way to authenticate.
It's a kind of a one-click. I get just
get to chew I get to click the sign-in
button um and the authentication flow
handles the rest. I'm not copying and
pasting API keys from some dashboard
into a JSON configuration file on my
machine or in some client. Um
It just smooths out kind of that use
case for the non-technical user. Um
It's not perfect. It's still a challenge
to implement dynamic client registration
um and there are a bunch of now services
that help um make make that easier.
Um but one of the things that we know
we've done with Turbo MCP is decidedly
implemented dynamic client registration
for developers so that it doesn't matter
how their MCP server implements auth,
the client can still authenticate the
user against their single sign-on IDP or
Okta or Keycloak or whatever.
Um and dynamic client registration only
has to be implemented by us and then MCP
server can connect to whatever upstream
uh
using other authentication schemes and
it reduces the amount of like complexity
and sprawl for the developer who's
trying to stand up an MCP server and
deploy it into their cloud
to not have to implement, you know, the
entire
you know, end-to-end OAuth flow.
Instead, they're able to just get a
token from our authorization server and
then I'll get off the races.
>> Nice. Nice. So that that allows them to
kind of go make that transition from
development to production much much much
much easier. Are there any other kind of
any other advice you'd give for
developers who are building MCP clients
and they want to take it to that next
step of okay, how do I actually how do I
actually push this so that people will
use it or host it for people? What what
would you say is kind of like the
biggest gotchas from from making that
transition to I want to make this work
to this needs to be a production level
grade
MCP server?
>> The spectrum of production is very wide
in my opinion. You've got, you know,
open source. You want to support, you
know, end users who can just freely
install and use an MCP server.
That still needs to be production ready
cuz, you know, they could be using it in
a bunch of different contexts.
And so, you know, just making sure
you're transparent with what the
implementation is doing, how it's
communicating to third parties, what
data is, you know,
requested of the upstream service to
provide back out of the client.
These are a little more for trust and
transparency. For enterprise setting,
I think you always have to be
considerate of the user being
non-technical. And so, if you're if
you're asking a, you know, person who
works in the marketing department to
generate an API key and, you know,
understand scopes,
it might be a little bit too much. And
so, I think thinking about how does this
user from an enterprise setting leverage
an easy path through an IDP or single
sign-on and how do I actually implement
that and how do I,
you know, integrate into their workflow
is is is really important. Otherwise,
you know, the friction is still a little
bit too high for for a number of users.
>> Yeah, no, absolutely. Let's talk about a
couple of things that kind of like build
on top of MCP servers. And one of the
things that I I really liked
and I I saw the demo
on on mcp.run was
was tasks. The ability to to set out a
task that actually goes you know, goes
behind in the background and
and performs an action typically through
a set of MCP servers that it has access
to. I love the fact that there's like
web hook support as well in there.
Um
What do we see as kind of like, you
know, next steps of people building on
top of these types of things? I'd love
to kind of like hear your take on tasks
about how people are how people are
using that today. And potentially even
touching on, you know, whether right now
we're very heavily using MCP servers for
for for text, but you know, can we go
beyond text for these types of
interactions? What are your thoughts on,
I guess, the evolving way which we use
MCP?
>> When we when we first started mcp.run,
you know, largely people were thinking
about okay, how do I just use this one
MCP server to automate a, you know,
action inside of this software. I really
want to to do a quick search. Even at
the time, you know, there was no web
searching inside these AI chat apps and
clients. So, an MCP server should enable
the model to go and search the web was
kind of a big deal.
Then it was clear that like the
multi-turn chat where
the user would supply a large prompt
and the AI would pick apart that prompt
and effectively create like a to-do
list, multiple steps that it would carry
out on its own. And each of those steps
could individually connect to server
that was different from step to step.
So, one step could be initial read from
Notion to try to find some data about a
project. And the second step was then go
and cross-reference a term from notion
in
a linear issue to look up some concrete
work that needed to be done. And then
the next step was to, you know, um
open up the code project on the on the
the laptop and start implementing that
feature. And then once the feature was
implemented, the next step would be to
update the ticket in linear to move it
from in progress to done.
And all in one prompt, the model was
able to discern which tools to call at
which time across its available MCP
servers.
Um and that was a real like lightbulb
moment that like
these are agents.
And all it was is a prompt with tools
attached. It's not a standalone,
you know, artifact. It's not a new code
base. It's just a prompt with tools. So,
what if we could create an environment,
a runtime, that would host a prompt and
allow you to attach tools to it and then
trigger it, um either through schedules
or through manual uh action or through a
webhook, uh that would basically say,
"Okay, you have an endpoint that allows
you to run a prompt and have it act get
access to tools." And that was where
tasks was born. Um it was basically kind
of like this
um non-directed graph, like a workflow
builder, that was just a prompt and
tools. And um so yeah, it kind of
competes with, you know, Zapier or
Integromat from kind of a workflow
automation perspective. Um but it is a
dramatic simplification of how to create
a workflow, which is just write a nice
prompt and give it tools and watch kind
of the magic happen behind the scenes.
>> Yeah, and I recommend I recommend to our
viewers to check it out because it's
it's such a slick
process. Uh and like he's like he say,
like, you know, Zapier that you know,
there's an amount you there's an amount
you have to do, obviously, to to to to
plug things together and manually wire
things together. But, this is, you know,
the the the task that you create here is
very free free-flowing.
And, you know, there's a lot of
decision-making that kind of like
happens in the background,
which is which is super cool to see.
>> Well, thank you. Yeah, I think um
many other options are still very much
in this kind of arrows and boxes era,
you know, create a component, drag an
arrow to the next thing, if this
happens, go to the next box, to the next
arrow.
And, the models are so good now um that
these decision-making steps or, you
know,
uh figuring out how to handle different
scenarios based on the return values of
a tool call
um are just kind of inherently part of
the models' capability and knowledge.
And, you don't need even like huge
foundation models to get this kind of
multi-tool call uh workflow. Even we're
seeing small language models work really
really well, knowing how to use tools
and sequence them uh in in the right
order to to actually
conduct a workflow accurately. Your
question about different modalities and
text kind of being the current I think
there's a lot of room to improve this um
and and largely it comes down to MCP
client kind of support and the
inconsistency across lots of different
MCP clients on how they present
um
other forms of media besides text. Uh
the protocol requires that multi- media
is encoded to base 64 strings. So, right
out of the gates, you know, you have
a additional step for a client to encode
multimedia and then ship it up to a
server for it then be decoded and used
in some way. There are
ways to get around that, but largely you
still have to encode the image or video
or GIF to some text to be sent over, you
know, the the the transport.
Um but I think there's some really
interesting use cases that could be
unlocked um if more clients were to
implement support for uh multimedia
handling both on the submission side
from the client to the server, uh but
also from the rendering side to take an
image back from an MCP server and show
it off um in the client. There's another
project that's unrelated to multimedia
necessarily, but uh is called MCPUI, um
which allows a client to interpret
signals from the MCP server as
render some novel interface inside of
the chat app or whatever the client is
hosted in.
So, the user could have more interesting
interactivity besides chat. So, instead
of just sending a message and getting a
message back, they'll be able to click a
button and get back a list of products.
And the list of products is rendered
just like it would be on an e-commerce
site uh with descriptions and prices and
purchase buttons. And, you know, an MCP
server could implement a full
application um that is entirely
implement rendered uh via MCPUI inside
of these various different clients. Um
so, I think there's again lots of room
for improvement and innovation um with
richer media types, but also as we
explore how to render UI um dynamically
um inside these clients, you'll see
really, really cool use cases emerge
that we just kind of can't even imagine
right now.
>> Very, very I guess that kind of like
leads me onto the I guess let's say the
final question.
What are we talking about? 11 months now
since MCP has been released by the time
this episode goes out. Um
wow, not even a year and the amount of
innovation
that and and and
you know, creation that's happened
around the MCP protocol
uh with, you know, the servers that have
been built and and and the work that's
gone around it has been has been has
been amazing. The the the pickup of that
has been incredible. What on earth are
we can we expect in an in another year?
What do you think what what do you What
do you What do you see the growth of
this
happening in the AI space? And I guess,
you know, will it be still such a big
thing in in a in a year's time or will
the next big thing
take all our attention away from from
MCPs?
>> Yeah, I'm not even going to try to
predict what the
future outside of MCP looks like and I
think there's still, you know,
so much adoption to be made that we've
only kind of seen the very tip of the
iceberg when it comes to how MCP
impacts, you know, the world.
A missing piece is to actually have more
services and data sources and things
that don't necessarily need
authentication like browsing the web.
You don't browse the web with an
identity all the time. You're going to
read articles or, you know, get updates
about some topic or read someone's blog.
Um
that you're not signed into a service
for necessarily. And MCP clients are
currently like over configured. You have
to be very, very explicit with which MCP
server are you using and how does it
get, you know, instantiated and what are
the tools available in it and and want
to approve this and that and have lots
of control and transparency over it. And
that's good. Um but I think there's just
lots of really, really interesting
autonomous capabilities and interactions
that we will see once people decide,
"I'm actually going to implement my
little app or my blog or my site as an
MCP server first and then MCP clients
can start to elect to
connect via MCP without this kind of
preemptive motion of the user adding an
MCP server to their client. Instead,
just like you browse the web today, you
render a web page and you click a link.
That link is really like what could be
an MCP server in a more free-form MCP
client. So now as you're just navigating
the content that comes back from MCP
servers, there could perhaps be an
embedded MCP server URL inside that
result, and the model could say, "Hey
client, connect to that server without
the user knowing, and automatically
start calling the tools and getting more
context, and you know, navigate through
a new web that is based upon MCP
entirely."
>> And you've got your own you base you've
essentially got your own curated web in
your new browser. What would be your new
gateway into
>> Yeah, well what would the browser for
MCP look like? What else needs to be
done on the client side to
you create that experience?
>> Well, one thing's for sure. I I agree
with you. It's it I've given up
predicting now. It's like what's the
point? What's the point of predicting,
right? But it's it's it's so curious to
to to have that have that think about
what what could be, and I'd love to I'd
love to invite you back in a year's
time, and we'll see how close we were.
>> Let's do it. In fact, lots of stuff has
probably already changed just in the
time we've been recording the podcast. I
got to I got to figure out what we
missed in just the hour or so.
>> I took a I took a 10-day vacation only
about a month and a half ago, and oh
gosh, never again. It's
it's just too hard. It's too hard to
catch to catch up.
>> It's it's crazy.
>> Yeah, yeah. Amazing, Steve. This has
been super insightful. Really really
appreciate your your your you know, your
your expertise in and around this space.
I'd very much recommend folks go and
have a look at run.dot uh run. It's
mcp.run, and and turbo mcp. Super super
interesting technologies.
Um where can people learn more about
that? I just presume they just go
straight to mcp.run?
>> You can go to mcp.run or delipso.ai and
get more information about both of these
products, or reach out to me on Twitter
and at nilslices,
or send us an email and just
hello@delipso.ai.
>> Sounds amazing. So absolutely do that. I
think it's a super interesting
technology. And uh thanks again, Steve.
Really, really appreciate the time.
>> Absolutely, Simon. Thanks for having me.
>> No worries. I hope you all enjoyed that.
And thanks for listening. And uh tune in
next time. Bye for now.